{
  "reference_number": "10995",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I feel that to treat CH4 as a flow gas, and therefore to let the agricultural sector off the hook for CH4 emissions would be a grave\n mistake. While I am sure there are political implications, I feel we must listen to the science. The fact is that CH4 is not only a far more\n\n potent gas in terms of short term warming, it also oxidizes to CO2 in the atmosphere and thus continues to warm in the longer term\n as well. So, any emission of CH4 (NOx as well for that matter), poses a far greater threat than if it were just CO2 emitted in the first\n\n place. Furthermore, to differentiate between recent and fossil carbon is a slippery slope in regard to CH4 especially. We must\n remember that there is also enough \"recent\" carbon locked up in the land to burn us to a sizzle. To allow agriculture an easy out\n would potentially give license to increased activities that continue to increase the removal of recent carbon into the atmosphere. We\n\n want to be locking more away rather than releasing more of that recent carbon. Allowing agriculture to continue business as usual is\n akin to burning our forests. We would be taking something that may have been locked away for 50-200 years, and re-releasing it. We\n MUST draw down both short term and long term gasses, regardless of if they come from recent or fossil flows. I feel this is kind of like\n\n asking us if we would rather flood the bathroom floor with water from the tub or the sink. The end result is still the same and it is what\n we want to avoid in the first place."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Strong safeguards cannot be emphasized enough. I feel it is a good idea to possibly be able to provide income streams to poor areas\n in exchange for protecting forests. However, since such areas and schemes are prone to injustice and corruption, this must be\n watched closely."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It should be allowed to bring the date forward, but not push it back."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes in theory, but it should not be able to be used as a political football or to kick the can down the road."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I do not like the idea, although I can imagine that there may be a circumstance where this may be useful. I do not like the idea of\ngiving a way out to lazy political leaders of the future."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most important thing is that we reach our goal. Along with that we must ensure that we take everyone with us and do not\nimpose disproportionate pain on the most vulnerable."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The commission will need teeth and power in order to force politicians to follow through with the task."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "I do not want political pressures to distort the market."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely. I feel we need a lot of scientists on board, and we should have people from varied and important sectors as well as people\nfrom all political stripes. This however must be balanced. We do not want the commission to be able to be stacked with people who\n\nwant to kick the can down the road. I think there must also be minimum criteria for membership; for instance, an individual MUST\nagree that anthropogenic climate change is real, and they must support real action- as a minimum. We cannot allow for voices that\n\nwould slow or halt progress."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I suggest that we not allow local councils to avoid liabilities from landfills. I know that some councils have up to 80% of their carbon\n\nliabilities in landfills. To not take these into account is to miss a very large portion of GHGs from the public sector."
    }
  ]
}
